<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>IA | Biostatistics edu</title><link>https://maicel.netlify.app/en/tags/ia/</link><atom:link href="https://maicel.netlify.app/en/tags/ia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>IA</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://maicel.netlify.app/media/icon_hu_551fbaee136b383e.png</url><title>IA</title><link>https://maicel.netlify.app/en/tags/ia/</link></image><item><title>MacroScope AI: Real-Time Nutrition Insights for Smarter Food Systems</title><link>https://maicel.netlify.app/en/project/plate-to-policy-real-time-ai-driven-insights-for-smarter-food-fortification/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://maicel.netlify.app/en/project/plate-to-policy-real-time-ai-driven-insights-for-smarter-food-fortification/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="transforming-plates-into-policies-ai-for-smarter-nutrition">Transforming Plates into Policies: AI for Smarter Nutrition&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>In a world where micronutrient deficiencies affect millions of people, large-scale food fortification (LSFF) has become one of the most effective public health interventions. However, for these initiatives to be truly successful, we need precise, timely, and contextualized data on what people actually consume. This is where our project comes into play: &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;MacroScope AI: Real-Time Nutrition Insights for Smarter Food Systems&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This project seeks to close critical data gaps in food fortification through the use of artificial intelligence (AI) and citizen participation. We will transform everyday food photos into actionable information, providing policymakers with tools to design more equitable, effective, and context-specific nutritional interventions.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="a-bridge-between-science-and-communities">A Bridge Between Science and Communities&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The key to this project lies in its ability to democratize data generation. Through an AI-powered mobile/web application, anyone will be able to capture images of their meals and contribute to a shared data ecosystem. These images will be analyzed by advanced image recognition models capable of identifying foods, estimating portion sizes, and calculating micronutrient consumption with high accuracy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But it’s not just about technology; it’s about inclusion. The platform is designed to be accessible in low-connectivity areas, offering offline functionality and multilingual support. This ensures that underrepresented groups are also included and reflected in the data.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="tools-for-better-decision-making">Tools for Better Decision-Making&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>One of the most exciting outcomes of this project is the creation of &lt;strong>LSFF data dashboards&lt;/strong> and a &lt;strong>policy support toolkit&lt;/strong>. These tools will allow policymakers to monitor the coverage of fortified foods, identify gaps in micronutrient consumption, and design targeted interventions for vulnerable populations.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="a-collaborative-ecosystem">A Collaborative Ecosystem&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>This project would not be possible without the collaboration of multiple actors. From AI experts, data scientists, nutritionists, and others, we have assembled a multidisciplinary team committed to social impact. Additionally, we work closely with ministries of health, agriculture, and the food industry, as well as NGOs and academic partners, to ensure that our solutions are technically robust, ethically responsible, and culturally relevant.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h4 id="join-us-in-this-nutritional-revolution">Join Us in this Nutritional Revolution&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Plate to Policy&amp;rdquo; is more than just a project; it is a movement toward a future where food fortification policies are based on real data, generated by the very communities they aim to benefit. Together, we can transform how we approach nutritional security and ensure that no one is left behind.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you’d like to learn more about how you can participate or collaborate, don’t hesitate to contact us! Together, we can build a healthier, fairer, and more sustainable world.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr></description></item></channel></rss>